Oh, jeez.
Yeah.
It's like death.
What in the world is up here?
Look at that.
Yeah, absolutely, man.
Maybe we'll find tools.
It's absolutely frightening.
Oh, my God.
Oh, golly.
Oh, my gosh!
Hell, maybe they
didn't abandon it.
Maybe they died.
It's all right. All
right, we're going.
We're gonna be
in a bad situation.
Let's be real quiet.
Don't wanna
garner any attention,
Wait, what is that?
On day one of the
35 day challenge.
Welcome to Africa.
Four teams took on an
unprecedented survival test.
Wow.
This is post
apocalyptic right here.
I feel like I'm starting this
challenge at the absolute
end of the world.
What?
-We got a mine.
-No kidding.
This is a weapon.
-Wow.
-Yeah.
After a close encounter
with a roaming elephant...
We are gonna need a bigger boma.
Steve and Alexa and Frank
scavenged a small junkyard
to make a fortified shelter.
-Yeah.
-Now that's a boma.
They were the first team
to secure a small food win,
but know they will need
more protein sources
to survive 35 days.
Fingers crossed.
Maybe we'll have some breakfast.
Oh, yeah.
Maybe a guinea fowl.
I'm gonna check my
bird trap I put in yesterday
using the bird cage that
we found at the old mine.
Nothing in it.
Is the bait still there?
The bait's still there.
Something might've
came up and hit the stick,
and then scared them off.
In an environment like this,
when there are no
natural resources,
we have to figure out
different ways to be able
to put food on the table.
So, uh, we're trying
to repurpose everything
that we can right now.
Holy!
Oh... oh!
He's just ripping out trees.
This elephant is so big,
he pushes trees
down with his face.
He uses his face to push
a full grown tree down.
He's seen us.
He's absolutely seen us.
Are we gonna stare off at
a full grown, full elephant?
That's what we are?
He is not scared of us at all.
That thing could
come in and trample us
and go about its day.
And then just turns and then,
-40 feet, he just disappears.
-Where did he go?
And you can't hear
him. You can't see him.
It's quite unnerving to
see the elephant again,
even though we now
have a fortified boma.
And again, it's
just a reminder that
you just have to have your
head in a swivel at all times
and be really careful with
what we're doing out here.
But at the same point,
we are getting hungry,
and we really need to find food.
It's probably prime time
to go check out that other
water source.
The other water source
has to be better than this,
and it's gonna be top
priority to go check that out
and see what it has to offer.
From their current camp,
the team will have to trek north
through lion country to reach
a secondary water source
just over a mile away.
It's not a hop,
skip, and a jump.
That's a journey.
-Take the water.
-Yeah.
Yeah.
-Water and the boat.
-Yeah.
You know, it's always a
risk versus reward situation.
Is it worth it for the
calories we're expending?
And the thing is, yes,
because this is the most
barren, dead area
I have ever been.
And that's intimidating.
Definitely back in Death Valley.
All right, I think
we need to get
some food in our bellies.
And I know there's
fish in that water hole.
So let's go do this.
Plan today is to go
down to the water hole,
check the passive fishing
line that Waz set out
to see if it works out.
If it doesn't, we're gonna
try to see if we can use
my mosquito net as a
fishing net, basically a backup.
How are you feeling?
I'm... I'm good.
I can just feel like I'm weak.
Yeah?
But I should be able to
still pull my own weight.
After one day in
the African heat,
Russell has struggled.
Talk about a bitch.
Forcing Waz and Teal
to shoulder the weight.
And then we're
gonna lift this up.
It's gonna be the roof.
He's using a lot of resources,
and he's not contributing
anything back in.
I didn't know how
worn out I was.
I'm exhausted, and I keep going.
So why can't he?
Wouldn't it be amazing if
there was a fish on that?
Nope.
But I know there's
fish in that water hole.
We're smarter than those fish.
We've gotta be
able to get them out.
Russ, we need to start doing
walkthroughs with the net.
In all honesty, I think that's
our best case scenario.
Yeah...
A little bit of trawl in there
and a little bit of grossness.
Let's work from this end, Russ.
We'll just slowly push
them towards the other end.
The heat takes it out of you.
The lack of nutrients.
And it's... it's making
it difficult for me.
But this is my fifth challenge,
so I'm out here for redemption.
It's insane.
The is that?
Snake got me. Gosh!
Oh, my God.
One more time.
And in South Africa, got
eliminated on Day One.
There goes my rope.
Wasn't proud of myself.
So it would mean the world to
me to complete this challenge
with my team and
close a chapter in my life.
Nothing. Not a fish in it.
Let's just walk back
and try again this way.
There's food right
there in that water.
And I want it to be right
here in my stomach.
And I'm gonna make that happen.
When this does dry out,
they gotta go somewhere.
We'll go check out
that... that wall and see
what sort of holes
it might have in it.
To protect themselves from
extreme weather and predators,
bottom feeders like catfish
and tilapia often bury themselves
in mud along the pond floor,
as well as in holes
along the bank.
So you wanna check the walls?
I start seeing on
the... one of the banks
that there might
be some little holes,
and I wanted to see if
maybe the fish are up
inside those holes.
-You touched something?
-Yeah.
Do you wanna pass
the net to me, real quick?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Here you go, bud.
The second that I
put my hand near it,
there was a fish
real close to it.
I'm starting to think
we need to change
our approach a little bit,
and my wheels are
definitely turning in relation
to what I've gotta do to
get these fish in the net.
Oh, one just swam
under my right hand.
Yeah, boy!
Oh, snap!
Yeah, boy, we got two.
Good job, bud.
-Hold this and that's enclosed.
-Yes, sir.
All right, two fish.
Those are tilapia.
As he was holding the bug
net close against the wall,
they get spooked
and try to swim away.
And as they swim out,
they get trapped in the net.
There you go.
Four!
They're getting
bigger every time, too.
Waz just started
cranking out fish.
Oh, my God. We're gonna eat.
Waz is a legend, and
he's a 10.0 for a reason.
Four over there, we got eight.
This is going stellar.
I mean, every scoop,
Waz is getting two
to three fish at a time.
Yes.
Oh!
Thirteen.
Lucky number 14th.
I'm so stoked.
So stoked.
I'm very happy that we got this.
This is gonna put some
fuel in the tank for us,
and hopefully that helps.
Russell get better soon.
Dude, that's...
I'm going for that net.
Go get it.
It's quite disappointing.
All right.
After making a temporary camp
next to their nearest
water source.
It really just put
us in a situation
where we're literally
just bait in a metal tube.
The team of Amber,
Joe, and Kel... Let's do it.
...plundered the remains
of a nearby hunting lodge
to begin work on a
more permanent shelter.
There's a bunch of wire mesh,
-we haven't got any of that...
-I'm gonna ask you...
to not interrupt me, please.
OK, I'm just not gonna talk
because I can barely get a
word in with you anyways.
Great, thank you.
The tensions now
threaten their team.
We have to survive
together as a team.
If we don't, how in the
hell are we gonna make this
in this wasteland?
Alright, so if this holds water,
we'll just fill this up
with dirty water today.
Take a full load of
dirty water up there.
OK.
Then, when we finish
that, we can boil it up there.
All right.
-Yeah, I know.
-I mean, who would've thought?
You know, a toilet cushion
would be the best thing.
You know, since
starting this challenge,
Amber and I definitely got
rolling together pretty quickly.
But Kel has just been a
struggle to connect with.
And I don't know
what causes the rift.
I don't know why, I...
I tried to set a good
boundary by saying,
"Hey, quit interrupting me."
And I, you know, I got
poked in the head with a stick.
It's really aggravating, and as
we go forward in this challenge
and the stakes get higher,
and it only gets harder,
it's causing a lot more conflict
than there even needs to be.
Let's try this out.
Boom.
It's so hot, we might as well
be as hydrated as possible.
It's gonna get hotter
throughout the day.
Everybody ready?
-Yep.
-Let's do it.
Get it while it's hot.
Let's go.
-Oof.
-It's hot.
This environment is
absolutely relentless.
We get so hot on the walk,
and there's so many thorns,
and so much barbed wire.
Oh, careful.
I don't wanna flap
you with my shoulders.
This is not a thorny one.
Trying to deal with
interpersonal relationships
that aren't working out
makes it even harder.
OK, Kelly. Let's go faster.
You can move,
pick it up, the pace.
The plan is to eventually
move to the other shelter,
and we're gonna get over
there to that broken down house
and we're gonna get
whatever we can scavenge
and bring it back
and just keep building.
But first, we gotta
figure out a way
to get them to work together
because I'm not
losing this team.
I've been with other
partners on challenges
where it's not always easy.
I don't care.
Drag it, pick it up,
whatever's easiest.
Just get the done.
Trish, shut up. Right now.
No, I'll never shut up.
You're being a dick.
And?
It was horrible.
And it was
detrimental to the team.
Hey, there's shade
here, Joe. So?
I really wanna have a talk
with Joe and with Kel together,
'cause this is definitely
gonna be a hindrance for us.
We really need
to button this up.
I know we all have different
perceptions of everything
and how situations come
across, which I fully respect.
But I think it's time that
you guys make amends,
'cause we really need this
dynamic to come together.
So, is there anything
you wanna say, Kel?
So, last night, I came
across a big branch
with thorns sticking out of it.
Very, very dangerous.
Couldn't even move.
If you stepped on it,
it wouldn't even
roll out of the way.
It would just impale any of us.
And so I tried to move
it, and it was so stuck.
And I tried to lift the fire up.
And then you, you
reacted and said
I woke you up by poking you.
And then you
grabbed it and threw it,
and you said a few words,
and said, "Don't talk to you."
And I said, "Well,
don't talk to me."
'Cause I mean, that just...
I have nobody in my
life that does that to me.
Not one person.
I will say for that
instance, you know,
I did react aggressively, 100%.
And that is part
to being in Africa.
You know, you jabbed
me in the back of the head
with a stick.
It startled me really bad.
My heart was racing.
I thought something
was in the boma,
or I was getting attacked.
And it's hard for me to
find that you empathize
with the fact that I got
jabbed in the head twice.
It was unintentional, but
I feel like I wouldn't have been
so offended by your reaction
if we hadn't had these
interactions since day one.
You're very curt, and I
get snide remarks from you,
and I don't... I don't enjoy it.
I think the best thing
for me is just to, uh...
Just to not engage with you.
-I just, I...
-Yeah ...I'm speaking.
So, I'm just gonna try
not to engage with you
unless it is vital
to our survival.
I don't mean you any ill will.
I don't harbor any
anger towards you, right?
I'm just frustrated
by this situation,
and you and I are
like oil and water,
personality wise,
and I hope that we
can get through it.
I do, because I want
you to make it through
this challenge too.
I tried attempting a peace
deal, and it did not work.
I'm trying to figure out
what we can do here,
and I do feel a lot of pressure
because I definitely am
the pivot point in this team.
We have two different
personalities here,
and we have to be
super strong, guys.
This is the place I've
ever been on a challenge.
This is our team. This
is our family right now.
We have to get through this.
Oh... Ah!
-What, thorn bushes?
-So many.
Oh, my God. This is wild.
It's like barbed wire.
And they're on the ground, too.
Yeah.
We're already into
a really hard hike,
and I don't know what's worse,
the heat or the thorns
that I'm picking up
with every second stab.
It's like I think my feet have
found every single thorn
in Africa,
but I'm just hoping that none
of them are festering in there.
Found throughout South Africa,
such plants as the Acacia tree
and the Sickle bush are
covered in sharp thorns
that can grow up
to two inches long
and secrete high
levels of tannic acid
as a defense mechanism.
I hope this is worth it, man.
Come to Africa, get
taken out by a thorn.
Looks like we might
got a clearing up here.
Oh, yeah.
Well, found the
other water source.
-Oh, it's like a swamp.
-Yeah.
There's life in this one.
-Oh, you see a turtle up there?
-There's food.
It was either a
turtle or a catfish.
We just got to our
second water source,
and it's a whole
different ballgame.
Just from looking at
the surface of the water,
we're seeing a lot of bubbles,
which means a lot of animals
are rubbing up
against the bottom,
releasing those gases.
So there's a lot of
protein sources here.
I'm seeing a lot of bird
tracks, too, guineas.
And I'm seeing... these
look like bush buck.
And I'm thinking now,
this spot right here,
is a really good
spot for a blind.
So Frank's a big hunter.
He brought his bow.
It's nice to have another
hunter out here with me
that kind of knows
what he's doing.
I can see everything from here.
If I could find a seat that
put me like right in here,
then I could literally,
I could shoot that
way or this way.
I'm very excited
about this water hole.
I know there's food in it
and to be able to set up
and hunt something that's
coming in and out of trails
here, it's looking good.
Holy!
There's a lizard
up in this tree.
-Oh, it's a monitor?
-Yeah, a monitor right up here.
It looks like a pretty
good sized one.
Yeah, I got him right here.
-You see it?
-Yep.
He's right there, man. I
got a perfect shot right now.
Do it.
-Got him.
-Yeah?
-Did you?
-Oh, no.
One of these is
going down the track.
-He's going around the branch.
-I know.
I think I just
completely missed him.
Oh, my God.
He's coming in the water.
Go, go, go, go, go!
Oh, no!
One of these is
going down the track.
-He's going around the branch.
-I know.
I think I just
completely missed him.
Oh, my God.
He's coming in the water.
Go, go, go, go!
How long can he
stay in there for?
Quite a while.
Monitor lizards are
excellent swimmers
and stay submerged underwater
by dramatically lowering
their metabolism,
reducing the need for oxygen.
Well, he has to come
out sooner or later, hey?
Yeah, but...
I think they got probably a
20, 30 minute breath hold.
All right.
I think he's right here.
There's something
moving in there,
where he, like, after
he threw the stick,
it was circling around.
Oh, well.
That was a hell
of a try, though.
Hey, man.
Food's food.
So close, yet so far away.
Sucks.
The sun's beating down,
and we waited for him
as long as we could.
He could've snuck
out a different angle.
But I tell you what...
there's nothing worse
than watching your
food run away from you.
Next time we come
here, put lines out,
get some good hunting in,
and hopefully make
something happen.
We all made a rule
that we weren't working
the hottest part of
the day, and look at us.
With predators
active in the area.
Oh, my gosh!
-That's crocodile feet?
-Yeah.
So this is already risky.
Wes, Miranda, and Stee have
been forced to drag material
from a distant farmhouse
in order to better
fortify their shelter.
Man, that was a hike.
So it took us, like,
three days to scavenge
all the things we needed
to be able to make
our structure complete.
But we have a general game plan.
We'll put the tin down to there.
Yeah.
So we're probably gonna
have to put some kind
-of ridge pole in the front.
-Yeah.
And we've got the tree there.
And then, that's it.
To enclose their shelter,
the survivalists plan to use
scavenged pieces of
steel pipe as ridge poles
with natural Y
branches as support
wooden pallets will be
used to form a sturdy wall,
while sheets of corrugated metal
are added to the roof and front,
providing a strong barrier
against the
elements and wildlife.
With this kind of landscape,
resources are minimal at best,
and so you really
have to be creative
to utilize man-made items
and items that are found
for our own betterment.
All right, that's a pretty
good ridge beam right there.
You need to
engineer survival here.
Let's give it a spacer.
Elephant dung, man.
It's just like WD
40 and duct tape.
Ultimately, we're
looking for safety,
a secure shelter for us
against the predators out here.
But also something to
block us from the elements.
It's extremely hot
during the day,
and then extremely
cold at night.
It's unforgiving here.
Gotcha, gotcha, gotcha. Got it?
Got this set?
The foot is under
it, so don't drop.
Ah!
-What happened?
-Smashed.
! Ah, you little bastard.
-Is it bleeding or broken?
-No, it's just red roll.
OK.
Yeah, there you go.
All righty.
We've had such progress
in just the past three days,
and it took hours of
thinking, and strategizing,
and planning and
engineering that we all three
contributed to.
So we not only have a
roof, but we have a room.
It's such a relief, because
everything else around it
is total apocalypse.
We have a regular,
like, a shelter.
Can you believe this?
Yes!
Jeez!
This is brilliant.
Well, I'm blown away
with how far we've gotten.
Oh, we done well, yeah?
-Nice.
-Yes.
-Air-Five.
-Good day.
I think our team is
really coming together.
We're rocking it.
Ramp it up.
Yeah, it's pretty
hot right now, man.
Oh, yeah? Let's go.
All right, let's go.
We really didn't get much
done on the shelter today.
The situation with Joe, though,
has just been challenging.
We're not really talking
directly to each other,
so I don't know
what to do about it,
and I don't know how much
longer I can handle this.
This is, like, a death march.
Feels like a death march.
This team is
falling apart quickly.
Nothing is getting done.
And, you know,
I feel bad for Kel.
When you're with people
who don't appreciate
what you really
bring to the table,
it really gets in
your heart and mind,
and it's really
detrimental to anybody
to experience that.
She treats you,
too, like her children.
I am so grateful for your
truth and your honesty.
Of course.
Eventually, she will be put in
her place, and she will realize
that she has to humble herself.
Good luck with that.
She's not queen bee.
I come out here in the
morning and just try to provide
for the team, and I feel
like they're just ungrateful
and it hurts my heart because
I worked so hard for them
and then they just whisper
about me, and I'm like...
I think my spirit is
just getting worn down.
I don't want Kel to go through
the same thing that I did,
and I want her to know
that I've got her back,
no matter what.
Kel, how you doing?
Tread lightly, girl.
These thorns are
quite ruthless, man.
Ouch!
It went in my eye.
In your eye?
In my eyeball.
Are you OK?
I got a thorn in my
eyeball, my actual eye.
It hurts really bad.
This is not good.
I am in panic mode, thinking,
"Oh my gosh, my eye,
just had a thorn to the eye."
I'm not really sure
what I'm gonna do here.
And then, immediately, just
everything starts to water.
Ugh, it's draining
through my nose now.
Ugh, gross.
It's just profusely coming
down, coming out of my nose.
And I'm like, this is not good.
I just may need the
medic to rinse my eye out.
Well, that's hot.
My eye's in a lot
of pain, though.
That's a bummer. I'm so sorry.
I've never felt
an eyeball pulse.
That's crazy.
But you can still see?
It hurts to open it.
Oh... I'm freaked out. I
have no idea what's going on.
All I know is I
can't open my eye.
And obviously, I
only have two of them.
I need my eyes.
-Hello.
-Hi, guys.
-It's hot.
-All right.
Could be better.
I had a... when I went to
like move one of the thorns,
I like lifted it off, and
when I lifted it off,
it came back and
hit me inside my eye.
-Like, painful.
-Can you open your eye at all?
-Like a little bit.
-A little bit.
Can you see me when
you open your eye?
-The other one.
-It's just a little blurry.
Just a little blurry, eh?
Sorry, water's
coming out my nose.
It won't stop draining.
Yeah, like right
here in the back.
Oh, that hurts.
Yeah, that hurts.
I know. I'm trying.
It's like my body's flinching.
OK. Sickle bush.
It's a type of bush with an
immense amount of thorns.
They excrete irritants and
cause localized infections
when they puncture the skin.
-Oh, ouch.
-Sorry.
Oh, God, that hurts though.
OK.
So tilt your head
back. Thank you.
An antibiotic eye wash
will help prevent an infection
from the tannins of a thorn
and should reduce the
swelling in a few days.
But if Amber's
symptoms intensify,
it could mean that the tannins
have penetrated the cornea,
requiring an optical scan
and more intensive treatments
to prevent permanent
vision damage.
OK. Crisis averted.
There's no thorn
in your eye still.
I have never felt eye
pain before in my life.
It is in so much pain,
I'm scared to try to open it,
but I'm gonna be
here for the team,
and I'm not gonna
let a thorn take me out.
-See you in a bit.
-All right.
I hope to not see
you again soon.
Man.
You never know what's
gonna happen out here.
I never thought I'd
be looking forward
to eating tilapia
out of a bog hole.
-Mmm.
-Looks good.
Oh.
Oh!
-You like it?
-I love it.
-Oh, that is good.
-Oh, yeah.
As we drink it, we're
taking in all those vitamins,
nutrients, the
saline from the eyes,
the fat from the brain.
I can literally say I'm
starting to feel rejuvenated.
Well, that's our first
bite of food out here,
but this is the thing
that breaks the seal
that is gonna open
up the rest of her.
Oh, yeah, it's like a good omen.
Yeah.
And I'll tell you what,
that broth in me, whoo,
I feel better.
Stuff like this is what
boosts your spirits, you know?
Then we definitely
need a new boma.
Exactly right.
Good fortune is coming.
Agreed.
Your poor eye.
Dude, I wanna try to
open it, but it just burns.
Just trying to see if
it looks a little puffy.
It looks a tiny bit puffier
than the other, but it's not.
I'm like, "How does it look?"
Oh, God, that burns so bad.
It's... your eye is
very nice and white.
It doesn't look anything
bad. Just keep it shut, man.
As I'm looking at Kel, I
just love her for who she is.
She's a great partner,
and she's caring.
So, I have a ton of
respect for her, there.
So... how do you feel
about the response you got
talking to Joe earlier?
I don't feel like he's...
able to respect me in the way
that I need for this challenge,
'cause it's already so hard.
-He's not gonna change.
-I know, I can tell that.
Joe and I are just not gonna
be able to, like, work this out,
and I know Joe's not gonna tap,
and I'm not gonna tap, so
we've gotta find a solution.
It's irreconcilable
differences, basically,
and it was like that.
Out the gate, so...
I would prefer to find
a new home, you know,
and maybe have a
better team dynamic.
And I didn't wanna
leave you, but...
I would prefer to
find a new home,
you know, and maybe have a
better... better team dynamic.
And I don't wanna
leave you, but...
I understand.
Kel's at a crossroad,
just like I was.
-Today, I am leaving.
-What?
I have to move forward,
and I've done what
I'm supposed to do.
When are you leaving?
Now.
Well, I hope you have
a great adventure.
Love you, babe.
Leaving them was
a risky decision.
Good luck.
But it was the
only option I had.
If you wanna go tomorrow
and leave and find a group,
I'd be honored
to take you there.
I'm really good at reading maps,
and I can make sure
you get there safe.
I'm not letting my
teammate go alone.
That would be super scary
for her going by herself
on a journey. I
know Joe's strong.
He'll be fine here.
But I'm gonna go with Kel
because we can't
fix this confrontation.
I'll just feel better knowing
you found a really good group.
And... We'll do it together.
We'll head out
tomorrow morning early.
OK.
This survival challenge alone
is an insurmountable
task to most people.
So I need people
around me that I can trust.
And it's obviously
just not happening
in this situation with Joe.
I'm talking to Kel and...
I'm sorry, love.
I'm gonna go find a
new crew, a new group,
and she's gonna escort me
to somewhere
where I fit in better.
And she's gonna come
back and be with you,
so you guys are
still a solid team.
And I'm just gonna
find a different situation
that works better for all of us.
Yeah, I'm sorry.
Our first time meeting was
in this stressful situation.
We just didn't gel.
I understand that you don't need
to add to more stress here.
And so your skills will advance.
Well, I appreciate
it. Thank you.
I understand that, you know,
those of us that are out here
are already really extreme
people for one reason
or another to take on
a challenge like this.
And when you're starving
and dehydrated and
sunburned like this,
we're definitely
not at our best,
but I just can't be around him.
It is a long trek, and
we have to be hydrated.
Absolutely.
So we have to be
ahead of the game.
I'm trying to make two lines
and get two lines in the water.
We checked out a
new water source,
which looks
like it's full of life,
a great hunting area.
We're gonna start
making some fishing lines.
Basically, we're getting
as prepared as we can
for tomorrow.
Oh, I can make a
gorge hook real quick.
You got your fishing line?
Yep.
Coming into this, the
item that I got out here
is my fishing line.
Unfortunately, there are
no hooks to go with that.
There's a massive
acacia thorn right there.
-Nice.
-Do you need two?
Two or one big one.
They're sharp, and we
need to cut it down a little bit.
What do you think,
three-quarter inches long?
Yeah, I would say
about maybe an inch.
An inch? I would go an inch.
How about those?
Yeah.
Perfect.
This is the most
primitive way of fishing.
Yeah.
But people use shards of bone,
and they'll use
these acacia needles,
and all sorts of things.
I think I ought to use a sinker.
Yep.
We got some little
nuts in that toolbox.
Oh, yeah. It'll
work perfect, yeah.
We have this old tool chest.
It's full of nuts and bolts
that would act as a sinker
for my static fishing.
So here we go.
Look at that.
Perfect.
You wanna tie your nut
on about a foot down,
-'cause it's not super deep.
-Right.
And there we go.
-How cool.
-Should be good.
I never thought I'd be
thankful for an acacia farm.
All right.
-I'll be thankful when it works.
-When it works, yeah.
Well, well.
We're in a new shelter,
and I'm telling you, what,
it is awesome.
We've got a wriggly tin
roof, and the last few nights
the temperature has
massively dropped,
so hopefully tonight
we feel a difference
and stay warm in here.
Literally, I have
my own room here,
and then we got
our little fire cranking.
We got our water.
We are all...
borderline starving
to death at this point,
so now we're just
gonna focus on food.
Something walking around.
I don't know what animal
that is, but there's something.
Can you see him?
I cannot see him,
but he's there.
I can hear the unmistakable
noise of trees being cracked
and pushed over, which
means there is an elephant.
Right there.
No way.
Oh, it's enormous!
It just pushed a huge tree over.
OK, I'm freaking out.
Here's the importance
of a bar of maroon
and a safe structure out here.
We should probably
get our fire going.
We've got a couple of
logs on the fire like this.
Everything sounds so close.
Oh, my gosh.
Holy!
This is so crazy.
Oh!
Oh my God.
OK...
This is so crazy.
This is the elephant
we heard last night,
and these are his giant tracks.
Pretty much what I
expect from Africa.
Big, strong, and
a little bit scary.
Actually, a lot of scary.
Hey, we all know this
conversation's coming,
but it's time to build
something a little bit bigger,
a little bit more functional.
The boma we're
living in right now,
it was always
gonna be temporary.
We did it there because
that's where Russell was laying
on the ground, and we didn't
want him to move too much,
so we just set a
temporary shelter up there.
But obviously, if there's
elephants around,
it makes you realize,
"Hey, we're right here
in the thick of it.
This is savage Africa,
and we're gonna be living in it.
Ooh, it's hot.
So I like the idea of moving
that boma down there
near the water.
Oh, hey, look, guys. I
can see some stuff up here.
-There is some cool stuff.
-What is it?
This looks like it used
to be an old corral.
Oh, nice.
So many things are
left here abandoned.
We discovered
there's a cow corral.
It has wire, barbed wire,
posts, things that we can use
to make our new boma
properly protected.
The boma's always
the bush with the thorns
and all that sort of stuff.
But what if we take this wire
and we make a real
strong animal proof fence?
Yeah.
Something they
can't get through,
something we can
still see in and out of.
This is huge.
You could fit 10 people in this.
We could use that
fence as a part of it.
Yeah, and then I'm gonna
put the corrugated tin
back onto that so we have a
nice waterproof shelter space
under here for a fire
and sleeping and stuff.
OK, sounds good.
Within 20 yards of
their water source,
the team plans to create
their new boma perimeter
using barbed wire
for extra protection,
then build their shelter off an
abandoned section of fence,
constructing two wooden
tripods for structural support
and salvaging sheets
of corrugated metal
for the walls and roof.
-Got it?
-Got it.
Perfect. OK, start,
but kind of slow.
Try and get it out. Why
don't you pull it taut?
I'm gonna put it
on this one here.
Yeah, OK.
Obviously, we'll secure
that a little bit better.
-Yeah.
-On it.
Right...
All right, hold on one
second. I'm wanna sit down.
Yeah, we've only been out
of the old boma for about 25,
30 minutes, and
Russell is sitting down,
he's breathing heavy.
I mean, it looks
like death again.
I think I'm gonna head
back to the shelter.
Every time I stand up,
I'm getting tunnel vision.
Uh, OK.
Russell is getting
exhausted already,
and he says he needs a
rest, but not just any rest.
Like, go back to
the old boma rest,
and that immediately makes,
you know, my heart sink
because I just have a feeling
we've lost him for the day.
This? This is tough.
This is testing my limits.
This is almost on a daily
basis is pushing me right up
to that edge.
-There's so much to do.
-I know.
Oh, God.
It hurts.
So currently, this is
what my eye is covered
in pus right now.
Oh... It hurts so bad.
I don't know...
what else to do except for...
I think I have an eye infection.
I really hope I'm
up for this today
because I am in so
much pain right now.
This will be the hardest
trek I've ever done
on any challenge.
But I'm willing to do this
because I really respect Kel
and just love her as a person,
and her and my partner Joe
are just not getting
along, which is super sad.
I really tried incredibly hard
to try to have a conversation,
figure out a way to make
amends, and then I'm realizing
it's just two personalities
that just aren't gonna match,
and the best thing for
Kel is to go to a new team.
Nothing like a sopping wet hide,
Amber coming with me
to try and help me get
to this next camp, especially
with what's going on
with her eye.
It's really hot out. She's
risking dehydration.
It's a huge ordeal.
I have super respect for
her and her strength in this.
So currently, we are here,
and there's an
abandoned building here.
-Mm-hmm.
-Yeah.
So our plan is, we're
gonna just head out here
and head towards that
waterhole right there, and hopefully
we find somebody.
To reach the next
nearest water source,
Amber must lead
Kel two miles east
across rugged terrain
dense with thorns, scorpions,
and the highly
venomous black mamba,
whose bite can turn
deadly within minutes
without antivenom.
All right, we're headed out.
Um, I'll meet you at home
tonight at the other place.
-Yeah, new and improved.
-OK.
You know, despite
Kel choosing to leave,
I feel real bad that...
that Amber has to
make that arduous walk
in the state that she's in.
And really, the only
thing I can do as a partner
for her when she gets
back is build that home up,
make it safe, make it secure.
Just give her a place of
rest, 'cause I'm 100% sure
she is just gonna be dying.
We're gonna head
out straight here.
We're gonna hit that
elephant game trail
and follow it up to the water.
Look at this termite mound.
This is insane, how big it is.
That's where black
mambas like to live.
Yeah.
That's very concerning.
They're not one
to mess with, at all.
We have to be
super cautious here.
There's so many nooks
and crannies for scorpions
or spiders or
snakes to come out,
so it's incredibly dangerous.
Oh, goodness.
Food is the number one
thing we have to worry about
right now.
But I'm not seeing a whole lot
of resources, and so that puts
a lot of pressure on me
to provide for my team.
I can see impalas
coming through that area,
taking in a drink, but there's,
like, no good cover at all.
Unless I'm behind
this and come out.
Let's think about that.
Everything about hunting
in Africa is very difficult.
That gives me a chance, maybe.
Every single animal
here is being hunted,
so they're always on alert.
Deadly predators, they're just
starving to death like we are
and wanna chomp on anything.
And so, if you can
find their patterns,
find their favorite trails,
that's gonna give you
an advantage and hopefully get
some food for me and the team.
This is a hook.
I found this...
pull tab off of a old can lid.
I personally have never had
success with it, but out here,
try anything, you know?
There we go.
Don't move.
Where'd he go?
Oh... Aha!
Yes.
I got more fish bait.
Oh, ideal! What did you catch?
-A lizard.
-Cool.
Hopefully we'll come
back bearing something.
Fingers crossed.
Oh. There's a belly slide.
And you can see his little feet.
See how it slides in?
Crocs, like, they migrate
from puddle to puddle,
like, daily.
So one day he may not be there,
and the next day he might be.
But we never really know.
And they have, like,
a bite force eight times
greater than a great white
and, you know, I'm not looking
to be someone's dinner.
That makes it more real now,
because I haven't seen it yet.
-That makes it real.
-Yeah.
He's here.
Well, let's get up there
then. Let's get in position.
Yeah.
We've just gotta be careful.
That's the first real sign
that I've seen that he's here,
and it is terrifying.
OK, I got it
secured to this one.
It looks like we're
making ourselves
our own little prison.
It looks like the way that a
prison wall would be topped
with barbed wire, but it
definitely is convincing
that it would keep anything out.
We got a good little
stretch of wall already, Teal.
Yeah. OK, this is working.
Sometimes, the
hardest part of motivation
-is getting a groove, you know?
-Mm-hmm.
Yeah, I'm not really sure,
to be honest with you.
The second that kid does,
like, 30 minutes of work,
or 40 minutes of work, he's out.
For the day.
I don't know if his
body's adept to doing
this type of work in
this type of environment.
Yeah.
I got a good team here,
and they're being
very supportive.
They're definitely a good...
good group of people.
I'm not doing as
much as I would like.
I feel guilty that, you
know, we're all out here,
we're all experienced
survivalists,
and I'm the one
that's down and out.
But I mean, I wanted to
accomplish so much out here.
So I feel the anxiety
and the stress.
And I feel like
something's wrong.
And... You know, I don't
know where the spots come in.
I mean...
I mean it's... I feel
like it's happening now.
I can feel it coming.
My fingertips are getting
numb. They're tingling.
That's all right.
You OK?
Breathe.
We've just been called
out to assess Russell.
He's having a panic attack.
We said to make him calm
down, make him breathe,
make him think
about his breaths.
Often triggered emotionally
by fear or anxiety,
a panic attack can elicit
intense physical effects,
such as a rapid heart
and shortness of breath.
But once the physical
symptoms subside,
there is rarely any
persistent medical risk.
So Russell was in some
distress when I got to him.
It's a bit of breathing
and anxiety,
but we have assessed
Russell's vitals.
He is stable for now,
and he is good to continue.
I'm just beat.
I can't see.
And I see spots.
Anytime I sit up,
stand up, walk.
That's why I've only been
able to do a little bit of work
helping the guys out
on the boma and stuff,
but I'm consuming
one third of all resources
but only putting
in 0.01% of effort.
This environment..
You know, some
people can handle it,
some people can't.
Apparently, I'm one of
the ones that can't do it.
How you tracking, Russ?
So, what's happening?
Oh, man.
I just can't get a
leg up out here.
Medics said my vitals
are fine, but I can't...
I can't function like this.
Yeah.
I'm gonna take it upon
myself to, uh, to tap.
As much as I, you know, I
wanted to see you at the end,
you gotta listen
to your body, man.
Obviously, nothing's more
important than your health.
All right.
Waz, I'm leaving
you with my bow.
Thank you, buddy.
Please, please, do
something with it.
Appreciate it.
Sad to see you go, bro.
Russell's tapping, and
I'm really sad to see him go.
This challenge is hard
enough, and having an extra
set of hands is always
something you need,
especially when we
have a long way to go.
To call this an
apocalyptic landscape
is an understatement.
I've survived in...
multiple different environments.
They all have got
canopies. The sun's not...
constantly there.
Out here, it just
doesn't go away.
My body let me down.
We're done.
The devil will sell
hell and live here.
I promise you.
Russell's gone.
He just really wasn't here.
-Yeah.
-I wish he had been able to be.
It's a new beginning for
us, though, I'll tell you.
We're not gonna be
having to worry too much
about making sure he's OK.
We can just focus on
what we need to focus on
to get us through.
Yeah, it feels good to
have that off our minds.
From here, moving forward,
it's all gonna be on Teal and I.
We're gonna have to
work so much harder
just to stay alive.
It's not just
surviving the animals,
it's not just
surviving the heat.
It's not just finding
a food source,
it's everything combined
in the most savage
primal environment
that I've ever been in my life.
Then there were two.
Yeah.
Ooh, it's a hot one today.
Got some fresh tracks, though.
Those are from today.
Warthog, maybe a porcupine.
-Awesome.
-Yeah.
Well, that's a perfect
natural blind right there.
I like it. I think
this is gonna be it.
We are back in the
secondary water source.
Lex and Steven are gonna
pop up some static fishing lines,
and I'm gonna sit there
and hunt for a couple hours.
So, this, I'm just gonna
kind of pop in here.
Gonna get ready to try to do
some hunting on the blind here.
Perfect.
All right, let's go
set these guys.
We've gotta get out there.
We've gotta take the shots.
We've gotta get the lines out.
And we've just gotta
hope and pray to the gods
for some food.
Boom.
Well, set it, forget it.
We should get back
and leave you to it.
Yeah, we need to
get out of your hair.
We need to stop leaving
human scent here.
We'll get the water
prepped and ready,
set for a couple hours.
See you back at camp.
Yeah, yeah, we'll
have water for you.
Thank you.
Got the blinds set up.
I got a shooting lane
there, shooting lane here,
shooting lane there.
Now it's time to get some
red meat, some protein.
My mouth is so dry.
My lips are like
literally stuck together.
This is quite
miserable out here, girl.
Yeah, I'm roasting.
Every step we take out
here is further and further
into this wasteland that is
just burned, burned, burned.
It's not stopped being
burned as far as we've seen.
It's... it's pretty daunting.
I'm just feeling the
heat, and I'm like,
"Ooh, I'm hoping I
can make it back."
Even if we eventually
find a new crew of people,
I'm a bit concerned that
they might've been having
the same issues we have,
and maybe they can't accept me
because they just don't
have the resources to.
I really feel like
my eye's on fire.
It's a really hard day,
especially when I
only have one eye.
But I'm gonna trek it
through and get her there
to the new group and
pray to God we find him.
There's a little
shade up here, girl.
Let's take a break. And we
need to drink some water.
Absolutely.
This place is desolate, man.
This is all we got.
We have just finished
drinking the last of our water,
and we're still really
thirsty and dehydrated.
That barely wet our whistle.
All right.
I just hope we find somebody.
I was really hoping for
a different experience
on this one.
I've got to watch two
partners go into the bush
and leave me
behind at the shelter.
Went right back to
where I was in Zambia,
my challenge on day five.
It's just getting worse.
I don't know. I wanna
tap out and go home.
All right. Sucks.
Having my partner tap
out and having to do it alone
made it increasingly
more difficult.
I had to quickly adapt
to doing all the chores,
trying to tend the
fire to stay awake.
So there was no sleep.
I don't have my whole
team, but I still have Amber.
So really, the only thing I
can do as a partner for her
when she gets back is build
that space up, build that home up,
make it safe, make it secure,
and just give her
a place of rest,
'cause I'm 100% sure she's...
she is just gonna be dying.
I think I'm gonna try
and utilize this bed frame.
I just can't... I can't
let another partner go.
Nice.
Keep off the ground.
For the first time ever.
I'm gonna put some of
that sheet metal that I got up
to block some of
the wind tonight.
I've gotta really dig deep.
Today is not a day
to rest and reflect.
Today is a day to
get up, to march,
and to start building,
and to build something
that is so incredible
that when Amber comes
home, she feels safe,
she feels at peace,
and she knows that I'm a
partner that's worth hanging on to.
Like a rusty glove.
It's been a slow morning so far.
We really have only
seen one impala.
A real small one.
And it didn't come
anywhere near close enough
for me to get a shot.
So I'm kind of disappointed.
The signs for game
are all over the place.
And so, I'm not... not
sure what happened
that they didn't
come in this morning.
It's getting too hot out here.
The fish are a lot like us.
Well, I don't know
about these fish.
They might be used to the abuse.
-But I'm out of breath.
-You're getting a bit hot.
Um, I'm just depleted.
It's so freaking hot here.
And quite frankly, this is
the longest I've not eaten.
Usually, I'm really upbeat
and, like, happy go lucky,
but my energy levels,
like, went into the woods
to die like the rest of
everything out here.
Hey, guys, how's it going?
It was kind of a
discouraging hunt.
My body's, like, starting
to feel the effects of...
-Hunger?
-Yeah, hunger.
Yeah, it has the brain working.
I was a V8.
Now I think I'm
missing a few cylinders.
You know, we did really
good at scavenging items,
but I think we kind of
put food on a back burner,
which I now see in hindsight
that maybe we
should've focused on, like,
the major survival
techniques instead of just,
like, creature comforts.
We haven't had
anything to eat in days.
The situation we're in
right now, it's very defeating.
But for someone to
succeed in this wasteland,
you have to have
mental fortitude,
you have to have guts of steel,
and you have to
have a desire to finish.
I have to call it
and go lay down.
It's so hot.
I think I'm gonna turn into
dust if I don't get there soon.
Oh, my gosh, I'm dying.
Been going forever.
We should be able to find it.
I just hope somebody's there.
Did you hear that?
What...? Are those voices?
Hello!
What is that?
Who the is that?
-Hello?
-Hello!
-Is that...
-All right.
Is there other naked people?
Holy. Here we go.
I got goosebumps.
Oh, my God.
Hi!
How we doing?
We're almost dead!
So I'm walking from the ponds,
and I'm walking up
to these two people.
And I'm thinking, they've
missing someone already.
Someone's dropped
out. Someone's tapped.
Someone's been
medically injured.
We've been walking.
We are so excited
to find you guys.
I had no idea who they were
until I actually
gave them a hug,
and then I realized
it was Amber,
somebody I've had as a
partner on a previous challenge.
It's, like, so cold.
You can see our
breath out there.
Yeah, it's really rough.
I don't think we're
sleeping at all tonight,
because all we can do
is, you know, fuel this fire
and then battle the rain.
You wouldn't
know this is Africa.
It's miserable.
Oh, I got a thorn in
my eye yesterday,
and I had mucus this
morning, so it's pretty infected.
Really going downhill
quickly, but I'm getting there.
I just can't see.
Not that we're not
happy to see you,
but why did you
actually end up moving?
Um, well, long story,
but before we get into it,
is there any way we can get
some water from you guys?
Yeah, sure, sure, sure, sure.
We just gotta go
back to our camp,
and we'll get you some.
There are only two survivalists.
You know something's happening,
and that caused
me a little concern.
I've got these.
We'll fill this up.
The water's nice
and cool right now.
It's been sitting for
a while, so it's good.
-Oh, my god.
-It feels so good.
-Just let it happen, girl.
-I know.
Believe me, all I
want is water on me.
This is a very
delicate situation.
I know Wes is a great person,
but it really throws a wrench
in your tractor when you're
trying to add another body
to take care of.
So I have to ask,
there's only two of you.
So, what's going on with that?
Well, that's why I wanted to
have a conversation with you,
'cause don't have much
time before I have to leave.
-Leave?
-Yeah.
Amber is escorting
me to you guys to see
if you'll accept
me in your camp,
because our other partner,
Joe, really didn't like me.
The truth is, their
personalities clash.
Joe and Kel, no
matter what we did,
they just kept bucking
heads up against each other.
We couldn't get anything done.
Yeah.
Unfortunately, I have no
hard feelings against him.
I just, I can't do this
as intense as this is.
And add that onto
it. It was unbearable.
Understood.
I've seen a lot of
merges at this point.
And there's always a
change, a change in dynamic.
Sometimes, it's for the better.
Sometimes, it's for the worse.
And so that, you know, that
caused me some concern
right there.
It's always just a
little increased stress
taking on a new person.
It was pretty rough,
and we were concerned.
We didn't know how you
would feel about taking her.
And here we are.
The truth is, I love her,
and she's a great partner.
And she always carries
the weight when we need it,
and she just wants to come out
here and be a great teammate.
You guys seem like
an awesome team.
I'd be blessed to
be here for sure.
And other than being
observant, resourceful,
and efficient, a really
fun, happy, loving person.
That's cool. I appreciate that.
Yeah, I think
that's a good idea.
Gentlemen, is that OK?
-All right.
-Well, we'll take you.
Thank you, guys.
-We are so excited.
-And we'll hydrate you, OK?
-Thank you!
-Sure.
I'm a mess right
now, but I'll get there.
-And you're going back tonight?
-Yes, I have to go back.
Joe has my bow right now.
He has all of my items there.
We built two homes. We
worked so hard for them,
and I don't wanna leave
my partnership stranded
-that is the truth.
-Yeah.
Amber says she's gotta go back.
And I understand it, but I
don't really understand it.
I mean, she just
hiked all the way to us.
And now to turn around
and go all the way back
in this heat, she's putting
herself at undue risk.
But that's her decision to make.
I hope you make it back safely.
Be safe tonight.
It's pretty daunting
to see Amber leave.
Her eye's in pain,
and it's really hot out.
She's risking dehydration.
I just really hope that
she makes it back safely.
-I love you.
-I love you, too, sweetheart.
Be safe.
Me and Stee are
gonna go get water.
-OK.
-Get the fire going.
-I'll get the fire going.
-Perfect.
I will try and get
some more firewood.
All right.
My initial impressions
of Kel are great,
but it makes me wonder what
happened back at their camp
in my mind, it takes two
people to cause a problem.
And, if that's the case,
I've got half the
problem in my camp.
-Wasn't expecting that.
-It's better than taking on two.
Ooh.
I feel like my eyeball is
gonna fall out of my head
right now.
Dang, it's hot in here.
It's too hot to stand.
I'm running wire
through these holes
so that I can lash
them to the posts.
It'll just help with when the
wind gusts come through,
not tear them off.
We're gonna have to use
those man made materials,
but this metal is rusted and
jagged and could cut you.
That danger of a sharp
metal surface, it's huge.
But Waz and I are a great
team, and moving forward,
our new shelter is
gonna be really important.
That is hot AF, my friend.
Try not to touch the metal.
Teal's been great as a partner.
We have a very similar mentality
when it comes to survival.
She's happy to just keep
working away at the jobs
that need to be done.
We get on quite well,
and it's just all positive,
marching forwards.
That'll work.
I think we've done a
pretty good job so far.
Yeah, we're making
a lot of progress.
But I'm tired, man.
Do you wanna sit in
the shade for a little bit?
Yeah.
We'll stay at the
old boma tonight
we didn't get the sides done.
All right.
I feel cooked.
It's definitely the
hardest day so far.
The heat of this
place is insane.
So back in camp, Steve
and I made the decision
that while Frank is out hunting,
we're gonna be
spending a lot of energy
trying to collect
enough firewood
to keep a fire burning so
that we can boil enough water
and have it ready to drink.
You know what would work good?
One of them wheels,
just so we get some
airflow under there.
Yeah, well, there's
one right there.
Yeah, that's gonna be perfect!
One man's trash is
another man's treasure.
We used a wheel that not
only helps us contain our fire
in one location, but helps us
boil water three times as fast.
-Nailed it.
-That's awesome.
So yeah, we need to get
at least a pot each a day,
like minimum.
And hydrate,
hydrate, hydrate today.
Fingers crossed
he gets something.
I know he's working
really, really hard.
Yeah.
The sun's high in the sky,
so it's like the
hottest part of the day.
These animals are just like me.
They need this water,
so they should be moving.
Oh-oh.
Here it is. Here it is.
Damn it.
I shot low.
That was my bad.
I should've waited.
I got too excited.
Too hungry to be missing.
My greatest survival
skill is that I fill the gaps.
If I could just
look at a situation
and I can tell what
needs to be done.
I can see that people
are doing these things,
and I automatically
know what my position is.
I can actually plug
in all those holes
and make the system function.
I feel like I'm borderline
malnourished at this point.
It just depends on how much
muscle and fat you've got
for your body to eat
while it deals with that.
Not eating for this long
and your body is, like,
-pretty different.
-Pissed.
I just want my body
to hang in there.
Yeah.
Come on, little fish.
Food's the top priority, OK?
We're all really
hungry right now.
We have a great
shelter. We have water.
We have everything but food.
Miranda's starving to death,
and now we have one
more person to feed.
Oh, I'm starting to
smell the ammonia.
Body's just about
burned up all my fat.
When the body is malnourished,
it begins to break down
muscle mass for energy,
a process which
releases ammonia,
a toxic compound that
seeps out through sweat.
Swallow, buddy, swallow it.
Hey...
Do you see that?
Is that the croc?
We finally see him.
And he's gone.
He was looking right at us.
This landscape is too deadly.
It's an apocalypse.
There's crocs in the water,
and so it makes
fishing really difficult.
And so we're really gonna
have to work on a plan,
just figure out how to
catch them and eat them.
Always something.
Come on, Mr. Crocodile.
Right now, I am
literally walking
at the hottest part of the day.
I am fumbling a little bit,
but I just to get back to Joe.
That's all I got.
I drank my water, not
even halfway there,
and I feel like my
eyeball is going to fall
out of my head right now.
It's pulsing so bad.
The throbbing in Amber's
eye could be indicative
of an infection, a
deep corneal abrasion,
or pressure from mucus
draining into her sinuses.
I'm really grateful.
Take Kel.
Now I'm just not sure if
it was such a smart idea,
with how hot it is,
but I just don't know
if I'm gonna make
it back all the way.
This shelter was built
by materials that were just
by that destroyed
lodge over there.
This place is just
death incarnate.
There is absolutely
no resources around.
So, man made materials
are making all the difference
in this challenge.
It's two-two by
fours, six nails,
13 corrugated metal
sheeting pieces,
and about 20 feet of wire.
I made it so large.
There's my fully extended reach,
you know, which
really helps in the heat.
You know, I've
got a lot of air here.
I've got airflow coming
through this thing when it's hot.
So I get this done.
I see the look on Amber's
face, and I know that
I did the right thing.
I look forward to
starting a life here
in the next 30 days.
Oh, God.
I gotta be honest,
it's super hard to see
these trails with one eye.
And I don't know what the heck
is gonna happen with my eye
because I am in so much pain,
it's throbbing
behind my eyeball.
I'm really struggling.
Oh, I see our house.
Thank God.
Joe?
Joe...
Oh, God! Oh, it looks so good.
Joe?
-Hey!
-Hi.
-How you feeling?
-This is horrible.
I'm have so much pain in my eye.
It just got worse on that walk.
I need a medic,
like, really bad.
Oh, God!
I'm in so much pain right now.
I'm actually scared.
I am, like, dying.
This place was just decimated
by that fire that came through.
I wonder what it
looked like before.
I think a lot of
people would say
it's a creepy place to be.
It's a super interesting
place for me to be.
Just... just trying to,
you know, work out
what happened here,
who used to live here,
whose house am I
standing in right now?
I wonder, what is this,
someone's bedroom once?
It almost looks like
the walls are pink.
Absolute other
end of the spectrum
from this savagery outside,
and now we have
the po... the possible,
like, a little girl's bedroom
that she played
with her toys in.
That's crazy to think about.
People have tried to build
a life in a place like this,
but it just became inhospitable.
So I think they
sort of just left
because they couldn't
handle it anymore.
I'm hoping that it's
a bit different for us.
I'm hoping we get to the end.
Surreal.
It's also absolutely terrifying.
-Hi, Amber.
-Hi.
-How are you feeling?
-It really hurts.
Just gonna... open up.
I'm not even gonna
touch on the inside.
-OK.
-Just on the cheek.
Yeah, that hurts.
OK.
Oh, God.
We've been having this
problem with Amber's eye
over the last 24 hours.
If you don't treat that,
you most definitely
would get an infection.
That, down the line, could
be much more severe.
OK, so I'm gonna put
some cream in your eye.
Yep.
Ooh!
-That thorn got me so good.
-Not better at all?
-No.
-OK.
In just 24 hours
since the injury,
the pain, pus, and
sensitivity to light
in Amber's eye has increased,
which are all signs
of serious infection.
We've been dealing with this
since yesterday now, Amber.
Yeah.
And obviously we're a
bit limited and restricted
in our capabilities in the bush.
You know, you say
you felt the thorn go
into the side of your eye.
-I don't see anything.
-Just right there.
And I can't see behind your eye.
OK, 'cause, if
there is something,
the longer we keep you
here, the worse it will get.
If any small amount
of thorn or debris
is lodged behind Amber's eye,
it could lead to
a severe infection
and permanent vision loss.
We're gonna be pulling you.
-You're going to a hospital.
-OK.
OK, so you fully understand
what I just said to you, Amber?
-Yeah.
-OK, so you won't be finishing.
I can't finish this with my eye.
It's time to get to the doctor.
-Get this checked out.
-OK.
Oh, it hurts so bad.
I feel like there really
is something in there.
I'm really glad we
got to do this together,
and I'm sorry that your
challenge had to end so soon.
The medical tap was
crushing to my heart.
I know how hard
my partner worked,
and I know we
could've made 35 days.
This is horrible out here.
It's desolate, there...
this heat is unforgiving.
But I need to go
get my eye looked at,
'cause I only have two of them.
I feel absolutely
horrible right now
that I have to leave my partner,
'cause I know it's
gonna be hard on him.
He lost two people in one day.
That's pretty harsh.
There's nothing I can do here.
I'm, like, devastated.
Like, this is day five.
Same on my last challenge,
only because this one's a
little bit bigger, guess what?
Two partners
on day five, I lost.
I'm on my own in Africa again.
I never, ever wanted
to be in this position
in my life, ever again.
It's hard, it's scary,
I have so much on
my shoulders right now.
Amber received antibiotics
to treat a potential infection
and a cornea scan
at a local hospital
revealed the absence of any
debris or scarring in her eye.
She was transported
back to The States
for further treatment, and
has since fully recovered
with no permanent damage.
I don't know what the next
30 days are gonna look like.
This is my surrounding... death.
As far as the eye
can see, nothingness.
I really wanna find a positive
space and place, but...
this challenge is
definitely the hardest thing
I've had to do.
I don't know what the
universe is trying to tell me,
but I've got 30 days
of time to reflect.
In this apocalyptic
scenario, we're in...
...you gotta last.
You gotta figure
out a way to last.